Jonathan Trumbull, Sr. Papers
Connecticut Historical Society
Jonathan Trumbull, Sr. Papers.
1637 - 1787
Connecticut Historical Society
Jonathan Trumbull, Sr.
Collection consists of personal and business correspondence; bills and accounts; sermon notes, diaries, and legal documents.
4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
Related Material
An index of catalog cards is available to aid access to this collection and material in other collections. Access is through writer, recipient and date. The card catalog is located in the Research Center reading room.
Microfilm copy available.
Biographical Sketch
Jonathan Trumbull, Sr. was born on October 12, 1710 in Lebanon, Connecticut, the second son of Joseph and Hannah (Higley) Trumble (sic). He received his early education from the second minister of the town, Samuel Welles. Welles moved to Boston shortly before Trumbull reached university age, which might explain why he attended Harvard instead of Yale, which was both nearer to home and less expensive. He completed his studies in 1727 and by 1731 was considering serving as Minister in Colchester, Connecticut. His plans were thwarted, however, by the death at sea of his elder brother, Joseph, and Jonathan took his brother's place in the family business.
Four years later, on December 9, 1735, Jonathan Trumbull married Faith Robinson, daughter of Rev. John Robinson of Duxbury, Massachusetts. Together they had four sons and two daughters.
Over the decades, Trumbull developed an extensive trading business. Unlike most colonial traders, who went through middle men in New York and Boston, he established direct connections with merchants in Great Britain. By the 1760s, Trumbull's business was very successful. However, in 1766 he began to suffer irreparable losses in trade and by 1769 he was virtually bankrupt and retired from business.
Despite his compromised financial position, the General Assembly of Connecticut elected Trumbull governor in 1769 upon the death of William Pitkin. Trumbull had enjoyed a long career in politics and public service, having first entered the General Assembly in 1733 and having served as a speaker in 1739. At the start of the hostilities with Great Britain in 1775, Trumbull was the only governor to support the position of the colonies. He had long been a supporter of colonial rights and during the war supplied General Washington with food, clothing, and munitions. Trumbull remained in the governor's seat until his retirement in 1784. His distinguished life came to an end on August 17, 1785.
Scope and Content
Collection consists largely of correspondence, letters, and supporting material written in both personal and official roles. Such correspondence is arranged chronologically. Also voluminous are documents relating to Trumbull's trading business: promissory notes, bills of lading, and accounts. Of special interest are notes Trumbull took on sermons, most of which were delivered at the church in Lebanon, Connecticut over the course of sixty years, from 1724 until his death in 1785. Some notable correspondents include Eleazer Fitch, Joseph Trumbull, Jonathan Trumbull, Jr., Benedict Arnold, George Washington, James Bowdoin, and John Newcomb.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into three series based largely on form.
Series I: Correspondence consists of correspondence written by and to Jonathan Trumbull, along with some legal documents concerning Joseph Trumble (sic), a folder of autograph clippings, and a copy of Lion Gardiner's Relation of the Pequot Wars.
Series II: Accounts, Bills and Receipts consists of promissory notes, bills of lading, and accounts.
Series III: Sermon notes, memo books, diaries consists of notes Jonathan Trumbull took on sermons, memorandum books, diaries, and accounts.
Collection is arranged chronologically within in each series.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is open, but additional material is not expected.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801.; Bowdoin, James, 1726-1790.; Fitch, Eleazer, 1726-1796.; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1740-1809.; Trumbull, Joseph, 1737-1778.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.
Subjects
Merchants Connecticut Lebanon.
Geographic Names
Connecticut Politics and government Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Sources.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed.
Contents:
- I. Correspondence
  - Letter of obligation from Jo[hn] Trumbull, et al., 1653 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence consisting of letter of obligation from Nathanael Bissell (sic) and testimony regarding Daniel Davison., 1653 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill of cost, Ammy Trumbull against Joseph Baker., 1726 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Religious notes., 1727 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Jonathan Trumbull., 1728 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Daybook, and a letter from Joseph Trumbull to Thom[as] Green., 1730-1731 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter of obligation., 1734 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Daybook., 1736 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Journal of proceedings., 1737 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Legal papers and correspondence, including that concerning Roger Wolcott, Thomas Hubbard, John Barnett., 1738-1749 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, including that from James Bowdoin, Samuel Sparrow, Josiah Porter, and Ebenezer Bushnell., 1750 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, including that from James Bowdoin, Joseph Pitkin, and Samuel Sparrow., 1751 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, including that from Samuel Sparrow, Joseph Pitkin, and Green and Walker., 1752 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, including that from Thomas Lane, Green and Walker, and Joseph Pitkin., 1753 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, including that from Green and Walker, Thomas Lane, John Williams, and Thomas Hubbard., 1754 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, including that from Isaac Woodworth, Caleb Jewett, and Thomas Lane., 1755 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, including that from Joshua Mauger, Thomas Hancock, and William Pitkin., 1756 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, including that from Thomas Wells, William Bowdoin, Green and Walker, and Samuel Sparrow., 1757 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, including that from Thomas Tyler, Abel Stitler, and Jacob Eliot., 1758 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, including that from Joseph Trumbull, Samuel Sparrow, and Nathanial Porter., 1759 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, including that from Abel Stiles, Lane and Booth, Joshua Mauger, Joseph Pitkin, and Samuel Whitney., 1760 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, including that from Jacob Eliot, Green and Walker, and John Alden., January-June 1761 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, including that from John Alden, William Williams, John Ledyard, and Silas Crane., July-December 1761 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, including that from John Newcomb, Samuel Gilbert, Silas Crane, Ebenezer Storer, and James Bowdoin., 1762 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, including that from John Williams, John Ledyard, John Patterson, and John Newcomb., 1763 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, including that from Abigail Metcalfe, John Ledyard, Joseph Trumbull, Lane and Booth, and David Hamilton., 1764 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, including that from Joseph Trumbull, Lane and Booth, G. Saltonstall, John Irving, and James Bowdoin., July-December 1764 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, including that from Jabez Huntington, Abel Stiles, Mary Torrey, John Hitchcock, and John Irving., 1765 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, including that from Alex Champion, Joseph Trumbull, Lane and Booth, and John Newcomb., 1766 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, including that from G. Saltonstall, John Williams, and Joseph Trumbull., January-June 1767 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, including that from Lane and Booth, William Read, and J. Huntington., July-December 1767 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, including that from Lane and Booth, Samuel Huntington, and John Graye (sic)., 1768 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, including that from John Irving, Matthew Griswold, H. Huntington, and James Bowdoin., 1769 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, including that from John Gray, J. Huntington, and John Lane., 1770 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, including that from J. Miller, William Hubbard, Champion and Hayley, Ezra Hommidieu, and John Gray., 1771 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, including that from J. Huntington, Jonathan Trumbull, and H[ugh] Leslie., 1772 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, including that from J. Huntington and Jonathan Trumbull., 1773 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, including that from Joseph Trumbull, Jonathan Trumbull, and Nathan Johnson., 1774 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, including that from Jonathan Trumbull and Benedict Arnold., January-June 1775 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from Jonathan Trumbull to such men as Silas Deane, Roger Sherman, and [George] Washington., July-December 1775 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from Jonathan Trumbull to such men as Shiebael Griswold, Nathaniel Buell, Jabez Huntington, and David Trumbull, as well as a proclamation from Jonathan Trumbull, serving as Governor of Connecticut., 1776 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Samuel Anderson, Walter Stewart, B[enedict] Arnold, and W. Heath., January-June 1777 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from such men as John Trumbull, E. Williams, Lynde Lord, and William Gardner., July-December 1777 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, E. Dyer, W. Greene, Artemas Ward, and Obadiah Johnson., 1778 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Samuel Brown, Samuel Culver, Joshua Huntington, and Oliver Ellsworth., 1779 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Note: Transcript available
  - Correspondence from such men as William Hunt, John Dishen, Oliver Ellsworth, and John Chipman., 1780 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, Heman Swift, J.W. Hamilton, and Henry Champion., 1781 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, John Tyler, John Dishen, B. Franklin, and Jan Gabriel Teagelaar., 1782 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, William Greene, Giles Mumford, and John Barclay., 1783 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Note: Transcriptions available.
  - Correspondence from such men as Abraham Gregory, Jonathan Trumbull, Ezra Stiles, and Simon Smith., 1784 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legal documents and correspondence from such men as Jonathan Trumbull, and Lane Son and Fraser., 1785-1787 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence from such men as E. Fitch, Daniel Lathrop, and J. Tisdale., 1750s-1780s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Copy of Lion Gardiner's Relation of the Pequot Wars., 1637-1663 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Autographs, primarily that of Jonathan Trumbull., 1710-1785 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- II. Bills, Receipts, and Accounts
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Thomas Flucker and James Bowdoin., 1722-1739 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Walker Harris, Ebenezer Webster, Thomas Cushing, and Theophilus Hall., 1740-1744 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Thomas Hubbard, Thomas Flucker, Jonathan Amory, James Calkin, and John Barrett., 1745-1749 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Aaron Thorp, Samuel Deming, Joel White, and Jon Mason., 1750 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Edward Bacon, Samuel Sparrow, and Joshua Abell., 1751 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Edward Bacon, James Grant, Thomas Bell, Joseph Marsh, and Green and Walker., 1752-1753 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as John Williams, Oliver Carpenter, Caleb Whitney, and James Grant., 1754 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as John Alden, Oliver Huntington, Isaac Sawyer, and Nathan Thompson., 1755 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Joseph Sluman, Joseph Waters, Joseph Winshipp, and Green and Walker., 1756 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Joseph Badcock, John Dewey, James Bowdoin, and John Huntington., 1757 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as George Wyllys, Ichabod Robinson, and Daniel Boyer., 1758 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Lane and Booth, Edward Holyoke, John Ledyard, and James Grant., 1759 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts, correspondence, and personal notes., 1754-1761 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Joshua Mauger, James Grant, John Bartlett, and John Robinson., 1760-1761 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as John Newcomb, John Webster, Richard Saltonstall, William Waterman, and James Grant., 1762-1763 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Jabez Huntington, John Graye (sic), Archippus Mackall, and Nathaniel Coffin., 1764-1765 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as eilsha Marsh, Nathaniel Coffin, Isaac Smith, and John Newcomb., 1766-1767 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as J. Huntington, Silas Sprague, Samuel Huntington, and Nathaniel Cushman., 1768-1769 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Isaac Williams, Amos Robinson, James Tisdale, Joel Marsh, and John Gray., 1770-1779 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Oliver Phelps, Ebenezer Geary, Joseph Loomis, and Abraham Bliss., 1780-1789 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Joseph Loomis, Samuel Trapp, James Tisdale, and Roger Wolcott., 1722-1785 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bills, receipts, accounts from such men as Samuel Huntington, James Lassell, and Abraham Bliss., 1722-1785 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- III. Sermon notes, Memo books, and Diaries
  - Sermon notes., 1724-1739 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Memo book., 1724-1784 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Sermon notes., c. 1730s (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Sermon notes., 1738 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Sermon notes., 1739 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sermon notes., 1740-1749 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Sermon notes., 1750-1759 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Sermon notes., 1760-1785 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sermon notes., 1770-1779 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Memo book., 1776 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sermon notes., 1780-1785 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Personal notes, correspondence, accounts., 1710-1785 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Sermon notes., 1724-1785 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Sermon notes., 1725-1731 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Note books., 1724-1785 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Journal., 1733 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Diary and account book., 1759-1762 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Diary., 1780-1785 (Box 11, Folder 7)